Dr. Samuel Gaucher

Consultant | Physicist | Data Scientist

Researcher with 6+ years of experience in nanotechnologies and quantum materials, solving the scaling challenges of the semiconductor industry. Demonstrated experience solving complex problems using ML, handling large datasets with Python. Goal-oriented mindset with outstanding teamwork skills, ideal to develop and maintain professional relationships in fast-paced environments.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

RISK MANAGEMENT CONSULTANT

Ernst & Young

- » Risk Management
- » Mathematical modeling

02.2016 - 11.2019

EXPERIMENTAL PHYSICIST

Paul-Drude-Institut für Festkörperelektronik (PDI)

- » Successfully managed a research project in quantum nanoelectronics.
- » Analyzed large and complex datasets using Python code.
- » Obtained groundbreaking results leading to 1 patent, 4 publications.
- » Communicated results to audience in 8+ international conferences.

01.2014 - 12.2015

EXPERIMENTAL PHYSICIST

McGill University

- » Developed novel nanofabrication methods to access exotic physics.
- » Established building blocks for a new type of quantum bit.
- » Contributed to results complied in 1 scientific publication.

01 2014 - 12 2015

TEACHING ASSISTANT

McGill University

- » Perfected mentoring skills by instructing 200+ undergraduate students.
- » Responsible to evaluate and grade academic work in physics.
- » Promoted academic success by giving constructive feedback.

2007 - 2021

MUSICIAN (Violin, Piano)

Self-employed

- » Performed with 3 classical/jazz ensembles in 100+ concerts and gigs.
- » Recorded 2 albums.
- » Taught 25+ students.

EDUCATION

04.2016 - 03.2021

Dr. rer. nat., PHYSICS (magna cum laude)

Humboldt Universität, Berlin

01.2014 - 12.2015

M.Sc., PHYSICS

McGill University, Montreal

09.2010 - 12.2013 | B.Sc., major PHYSICS, minor PHILOSOPHY

McGill University, Montreal

ACTIVITIES

- » Spokesperson of the graduate students at PDI (2017-2019)
- » Volunteer for the Falling Walls Foundation during the Berlin Science Week (2019)
- » Young Entrepreneurs in Science Workshop in Leipzig (2019)
- » NSERC-CREATE Training Program in Integrated Sensor Systems (2015)
- » Organizing member of the Physics Games at McGill University (2015)
- » High-school student representative/student body president (2001-2010)



CONTACT DETAILS

Email

sam@gaucher.io

Mobile

+49 174 3857521

LinkedIn

linkedin.com/in/samuelgaucher

Website

https://gaucher.io

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

Python TensorFlow/Keras

Computer Vision

MATLAB

HTML/JS/CSS

Raspberry Pi

Sensors

Communication

Leadership

Entrepreneurship

EXPERTISE

Data Visualization

Machine Learning

Nanotechnologies

Quantum Information

LANGUAGES

French (native)

Enalish

German -----

Italian